# 它真的是像一个玫瑰花一样的饼
This cake literally looks like a rose
# 但是它和云南的鲜花饼不同的是
The difference between this rose cake and the flower cake in Yunnan is
# 它的块头真的是特别大个
That this one is really big
# 我不敢举太高 我怕一不小心把玫瑰饼全部打翻
I don’t want to hold it too high because I’m afraid to knock over the whole cake
# 玫瑰花瓣一片片，飘落在眼前
Pieces of rose petals are falling in front of my eyes
# 青海·西宁
Xining, Qinghai
# 雪鱼现在在青海西宁
I’m currently in Xining, Qinghai
# 待会呢 我们要去吃的是玫瑰花饼
We are going to eat the local rose cake in a few minutes
# 这个玫瑰花饼和云南的玫瑰花饼 可截然不同
The rose cake here and the one in Yunnan are totally different
# 待会看一看 庐山真面目
We’ll see the real deal in a moment
# 绝对会刷新你对玫瑰花饼的认知
It will definitely challenge your usual understanding of rose cake
# 待会我要去的是一个菜市场
Where I’m going is a farmers’ market
# 里面有一家专门做玫瑰饼的小店
There is a small street food shop specialised in making rose cakes inside
# 是这种前店后厨的模式
Counter in the front and kitchen in the back
# 做好的玫瑰饼呢 会拿到前面切完再卖
The rose cake coming out of the oven will be brought to the front and cut into portions before selling to the public
# 这么大的一个 切完 也只能切成八份
It can only be cut into 8 portions even it’s already this big
# 如果你前面站着八个人 那你一定会等下一个玫瑰饼
If there are 8 people queueing in the front, you will have to wait for the next cake
# 55元3角 给55元吧
55 yuan and 30 cents. Take it home for 55
# 回去先不要系 晾凉了再系上
Don’t tighten the bag immediately after you get home. Wait until it’s cold
# 它已经碎了
It has already broken
# 原来是像花一样的美食
The cake used to look like a flower
# 现在碎成了三瓣
Now it has broken into three chunks
# 刚才我已经偷偷吃了一两块
I sneaked two pieces just now
# 可能就是因为它太容易碎了
Probably because it’s too fragile
# 所以说 你看 老板都是提前切好
The shopkeeper has to cut the cake for you in advance
# 你只能从他切好的块当中去选
And you can only choose from the cut portions
# 不能够再切了 再切就碎成渣了
You can’t cut it any further, or it will turn into broken bits
# 接下来雪鱼呀给大家看一下
Now, let me show you
# 这个玫瑰花饼有多厚
How thick this rose cake is
# 它的横切面还是很好看的
The cut side actually looks pretty lovely
# 真的是这么厚
The cake is REALLY thick
# 有一圈圈的花纹
There is a pattern of circles here
# 这个玫瑰饼是把底面放在了上面
The rose cake is upside down here
# 其实下面 才是它的上面
The top side is actually on the bottom
# 我说袋子的下面才是（玫瑰饼）的上面
I mean the top side of the rose cake is on the bottom of the bag
# 现在我把玫瑰饼正过来了
Now I have turned it over
# 玫瑰饼就是 没切的时候 外形像一朵花
The shape of the whole cake is like a rose before it’s cut
# 但是切开之后 它的侧面更像一朵花
But once cut, the side of the cake resembles a rose more
# 这样的渣渣都觉得好吃
Even these broken bits taste great
# 它的颜色就是 红 黄 黑相间的
The colour is a mix of red, yellow and black
# 外面是硬壳 烤的比较坚硬
The outer shell is crusty and crunchy
# 但是 它下面的内瓤是一层层的
But underneath the shell are layers of goodness
# 哎呦 一碰就掉啊 我们就吃它这一块吧
Wow, it’s so delicate. Let’s just eat it
# 来
Here we go
# 玫瑰花瓣一片片 飘落在眼前
Pieces of rose petals are falling in front of my eyes
# 它这个玫瑰饼 算不上多甜
This rose cake is, to be honest, not too sweet
# （从外面看颜色）颜色和枣糕很像 闻起来的味道也很像
The colour (on the outside) is similar to the date cake, so is the smell
# 但是吃一口发现 它们的味道真的是截然不同
But once you take a bite, they have completely different flavours
# 像枣糕这种就是闻着甜 吃起来更甜
The date cake smells sweet, and tastes even sweeter
# 但是这个（不是）
Totally not the case for this rose cake
# 它的甜度只比  就是嚼馒头的时候
It’s only slightly sweeter than the maltose
# 那个麦芽糖的甜味稍稍高一点
When you chew mantou (aka Chinese steamed buns)
# 根本就不算很甜
Not so sweet at all
# 美食不仅可以吃 还可以用来享受
You can not only eat, but also enjoy this gourmet food
# 它好像美食届的七彩丹霞地貌
It is like the landscape of the colourful Danxia
# 它的味道很奇特
And it has such a unique taste
# 既有面包的暄软 又像千层饼一样的酥脆
Soft like bread, crunchy like mille-feuille
# 还有就是 像玫瑰饼的甜美
And sweet as a rose cake
# 刚才吃的玫瑰饼 吃的晕头转向的
I’m so confused by the rose cake I just ate
# 因为它的味道是既甜 又咸
Because it tastes both sweet and savoury at the same time
# 甜是很容易理解的 里面放了玫瑰酱
It’s easy to understand the sweetness as it has rose sauce in it
# 这个咸 我想了老半天
But I just can’t comprehend, from my perspective
# 好像不太明白 它为什么是咸的
Why it is also savoury
# 接下来雪鱼就是 返回原来的地方
So next, I’ll go back to the shop
# 问一问老板
And ask the shopkeeper
# 里面还有什么样的材料是我不知道的
If there are any secret ingredients in there that I don’t know
# 就是里面加了胡麻 还有姜黄 还有一种叫什么
So, there are sesame and turmeric. What’s the other one called?
# 红曲
Red yeast
# 这实际上就是 八月十五我们蒸的月饼变成烤的了
In fact, it’s similar to the mooncake. We just bake it instead of steaming it
# 蒸的东西放不住 这个能够放一个礼拜
Steamed foods don’t last long, but this cake can last a week
# 蒸的东西 两三天边上就干了
The edge will dry out within 2 to 3 days if you steam it
# 它就是 以前我们那用老酵面做的 发面做的
The dough is made from the old starter
# 有些原料 是从老家 自产运过来的
Some ingredients are brought here from our hometown by ourselves
# 全汁原味 就算绿色产品吧
All natural and organic. We shall count them as green products
# 除了了解里面放了什么原料之外
Apart from knowing what ingredients have been put inside
# 还意识到 自己原来吃了个月饼
I also realise that I just ate a mooncake
# 好了 接下来雪鱼将要去下一个地方了
Alright, I’ll be on my way to the next place
# 关 注
# 雪 鱼  探 店
Follow Xueyu - China Food Travel